<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A voice from the temple to the higher povvers. Wherein is shewed, that it is the work and duty of saints, to search the prophesies and visions of holy Scripture, which concern the later times: and that Jesus Christ will reveal the understanding of them, neer the end of their accomplishment. And so much, is here clearly proved, and the objections to the contrary answered. Also severall prophesies are here opened, concerning the time of the end; as what is the present work of the Lord in the world: and wherein the saints (whether the higher powers or others) are now to move and follow him. Likwise [sic] what will be the work of the Lord forward, and all along from year to year, till the mysterie of God be finished, both among the Christian gentiles, and Jewes. By John Canne.</title>
            <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C443B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E699_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207049</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866125</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866125</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E699[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A voice from the temple to the higher povvers. Wherein is shewed, that it is the work and duty of saints, to search the prophesies and visions of holy Scripture, which concern the later times: and that Jesus Christ will reveal the understanding of them, neer the end of their accomplishment. And so much, is here clearly proved, and the objections to the contrary answered. Also severall prophesies are here opened, concerning the time of the end; as what is the present work of the Lord in the world: and wherein the saints (whether the higher powers or others) are now to move and follow him. Likwise [sic] what will be the work of the Lord forward, and all along from year to year, till the mysterie of God be finished, both among the Christian gentiles, and Jewes. By John Canne.</title>
                  <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons next door to the gilded Lyon in Aldersgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "[illegible] June. 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118389:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VOICE From the Temple TO THE Higher Povvers.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed, that it is the work and duty of Saints, to ſearch the <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> and <hi>Viſions</hi> of holy Scripture, which concern the <hi>Later Times:</hi> And that Jeſus Chriſt will reveal the underſtanding of them, neer the end of their accompliſhment. And ſo much, is here clearly proved, and the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the contrary anſwered.</p>
            <p>ALSO Severall <hi>Propheſies</hi> are here opened, concerning <hi>the Time of the End;</hi> As what is the preſent work of the Lord in the world: And wherein the Saints (whether the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> or others) are now to move and follow him. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what will be the work of the Lord forward, and all along from year to year, <hi>till the Myſterie</hi> of God be finiſhed, both among the Chriſtian <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>Jewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Canne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Pet. 3.3, 4.</hi>
                  </bibl> There ſhall come in the laſt dayes mockers, ſaying, where is the promiſe of his coming.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Job 21.3.</hi>
                  </bibl> Suffer me that I may ſpeake, and after that I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, mocke on.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Dan. 22.10.</hi>
                  </bibl> But the wicked ſhall doe wickedly &amp; none of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall underſtand, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons,</hi> next door to the gilded Lyon in <hi>Alderſgate</hi> ſtreet, 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118389:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118389:2"/>
            <head>TO His Excellency the Lord General CROMWEL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was moſt unhappily done of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to put the letter into his boſome, which he ſhould have read before he went unto the Conſull. I ſhall humbly deſire your <hi>Excellency</hi> (in the midſt of your great Affaires) to read over this ſhort <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> which was intended in publiſhing, ſpecially for you, as being thereunto encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by your Honour. Had thoſe, whoſe Crownes are now fallen, and their places have caſt them out, not laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide <hi>Daniel,</hi> and other Propheſies of the <hi>later Times,</hi> but day and night meditated therein, and ſo known <hi>the ſignes of the Son of man,</hi> their glory would not ſo ſoone have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from them. But truſting to lying vanities, they forſooke their owne mercies.</p>
            <p>As for other Bookes of humane wiſdome and State-poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, they are almoſt now like an <hi>old Almanack,</hi> out of date, most improper and uſeleſſe to the great worke of this age. And therefore ſuch as deſire to ſtand, and not to be loſt in the night of Errour and ſhame, muſt ſearch the great Booke of Gods Counſell: for there they ſhall know (and no where elſe) what the worke is of their owne generation. It
<pb facs="tcp:118389:3"/>is not enough that a man meanes well, and reſolves to doe honeſt and juſt things, but he is to conſider whether the thing which he propoſeth next to do, be his worke, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the time in which he lives.</p>
            <p>It was in <hi>Davids</hi> heart to build God an houſe, and the worke ſeem'd to <hi>Nathan</hi> to be ſo pious and good, as he gave him encouragement to goe forward with it. Nevertheleſſe <hi>David</hi> here was miſtaken, and the Prophet too: For <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was not the man, but <hi>Solomon,</hi> appointed for that buſineſſe. As Gods thoughts are not our thoughts, nor his wayes our ways, ſo it oft-times falls out: what our thoughts are buſied moſt about, and ſticke faſteſt too, that is not the thing which the Lord intends we ſhall do, but he hath ſome other employment and ſervice for us.</p>
            <p>My Lord, it is for this end, I write thus to you, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I hope you intend a great deale of good to the Nation, and thinke of nothing but what is honeſt, juſt, pure, and of good report: yet one thing is needfull, namely, that you ſearch <hi>the Propheſies of the later times,</hi> to finde out what is your worke, as now proper to you: That ſo you may doe <hi>that good, that acceptable, and perfect wil of God</hi> in your generation. <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant whom his Lord when he cometh, ſhall find SO DOING:</hi> Not only doing, but doing ſo and ſo.</p>
            <p>That it was your worke (and appointed to you of God) to be a happy inſtrument for the diſſolving the laſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is not only cleare to me, but ſomething is here ſaid in the juſtification of it.</p>
            <p>But now (my Lord) the <hi>great Queſtion</hi> is, what is next? I have purpoſely publiſhed this Booke, to anſwer this great Queſtion, to wit, that your <hi>Excellency</hi> and others in place, may ſee what my opinion is, (and how grounded
<pb facs="tcp:118389:3"/>upon the word) concerning the Lords works, and working at this time, and wherein you and others are to move, and follow the Lamb. I ſhall not ſpeake any thing concerning the choſe of the <hi>new Governours</hi> which lies before you: Only this; by knowing what is the Lords worke which he is now doing amongſt us, and carrying forth in the world, it may be ſomewhat uſefull to your <hi>Excellency</hi> in your choiſe, as to call out ſuch men, as are beſt principled and qualified for <hi>THAT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, Thoſe great <hi>Stateſmen</hi> who are laid aſide, &amp; lie in duſt, under the guilt and ſhame of their actions, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not deep policie, ſtrong reaſon, worldly wiſdome, poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Councellours, and large advantages of the time: but this they wanted (which was their ruine) they were not like the <hi>children of Iſſachar, men that had the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Times, to know what Iſrael ought to doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is, that not only my ſelf, but many more who love you truly and dearely, earnestly deſire (and begg it daily of God for you) that thoſe Propheſies which ſpeak out the work of God to be done now in the world, may be ſearcht by you, and clearly opened to you. Methinks I ſhould finde you in that <hi>voyce from heaven, ſaying, Come out of her my people:</hi> and to be one of the <hi>Angels pouring out the fifth Viall.</hi> About the time of Chriſts Incarnation, there was a great expectation amongſt the Jewes of the coming of the Meſſiah: For they knew by former Propheſies that he was then to come.</p>
            <p>This voyce from Heaven, and the fifth Angel is already come: but there is now an expectation to have that Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie perfected. And if the Lord ſhall be pleaſed to perfect by you, the good worke which he hath made you inſtrumentall
<pb facs="tcp:118389:4"/>in, that is, to be his, and our <hi>Generall</hi> still, for the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the laſt vengeance upon the two perſecuting powers of the world, <hi>viz.</hi> Kingly and Antichriſtian, it will be ſuch an honour as few of the ſonnes of men ever had.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I ſhall cloſe with this; there is no work for you in the grave, it muſt be done on this ſide: It might have been a Motto ſet upon <hi>Davids</hi> Sepulchre; <hi>After hee had ſerved his owne Generation by the will of God, he fell aſleep;</hi> he fell not aſleep till he had ſerved his Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This ſhall be my prayer, that in life and death it may be ſo with you. Even doe the worke of him that ſent you whilſt it is today; and when you are gathered to your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that the memorie of your name may be precious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints, as <hi>Davids</hi> was in Iſrael. And thus prays he who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Excellencies moſt humble Servant,</hi> John Canne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118389:4"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honourable, Colonell <hi>Robert Overton,</hi> Governour of <hi>Hull,</hi> and his Religious <hi>Lady,</hi> with all my other dear Chriſtian friends in, and about <hi>Hull.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT hath been the great deſire of ſome of you, that I would pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to the world <hi>My Notes upon Daniel.</hi> I had no intent when I preacht them, that they ſhould have been further known, or more common then amongſt you. Theſe <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> and <hi>Revolutions</hi> in our Nation, have changed my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and ſomething I have begun: As not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to beare witneſſe before the world, to what more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately I delivered to you: For the ſeverall Cenſures of men otherwiſe minded, I can well beare them; for I did ſit downe firſt, and count the coſt; Beſides for men <hi>to ſpeak evill of thoſe things which they know not,</hi> it is uſuall. <hi>But wiſdome is juſtified of her children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sirs,</hi> I cannot without much thankefulneſſe to God, and comfort to my ſelfe but remember you, ſpecially your moſt earneſt and conſtant ſeeking of God, to have <hi>the Book opened, and the Seales loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> that you might ſee your worke, and know how to Act for Chriſt in your Generation. I make mention of this, that your zeale may provoke others, and ſtir them up <hi>to aske wiſdome of God,</hi> and for <hi>Zions</hi> ſake not to hold their peace, and for <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſake not to give him reſt, till he eſtabliſh and make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth. For my part, I can ſpeak it to Gods glory, I have found all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in opening the Propheſies of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> to you, the anſwer of your prayers, and the fruit of your faith abundantly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſoule.</p>
            <p>I know theſe things when they were delivered, offended the <hi>Prieſts</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118389:5"/>in that Countrey, and in likelihood, being made now more publique, will increaſe their rage and blaſphemie againſt the God of Heaven, becauſe of their pains and ſores. It is not deſtruction I wiſh them, but that the Lord will give them Repentance from dead workes, and that they would forſake their unſanctified places and ſtandings, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people any longer, by their lies and beaſtly vanities, I ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fierce anger of the Lord, and the wrath of the Lamb come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>I hope there will be ſhortly ſome effectuall meanes uſed, to remove from the people the heavieſt burthen, and ſoreſt plague that lies upon them, which is <hi>a generation of Prieſts,</hi> that fatten the people for the day of ſlaughter: For my part, what Intereſt I have either with God or men, I ſhall endeavour to improve it to the utmoſt, That <hi>the Foxes, both the old and the young Cubs, which ſpoile the Vines and the tender Grapes, may be taken.</hi> I know people ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, though they complain of other Oppreſſions and burdens, and would willingly be eaſed of them: yet here they have no feeling, and therefore they are the more to be pittied, and the ſooner helped, in not apprehending what is the greateſt miſery they lie under. Thoſe who have lately ſhewed ſo much good affection to have the Goſpell advanced in <hi>New-England,</hi> I hope they will be farre more enlarged in their bowels, for the converſion of poore Heathens in our owne Land, that the people which ſit here in darkneſſe, may ſee a great light, and to them which ſit in the region and ſhadow of death, light may ſpring up.</p>
            <p>Deare friends, I ſhall not write much, though I could ſay much in your behalfe, as being lights among a crooked and froward generation, walking in the life and power of Religion, where others are meer For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſts. Beſides, you have not been aſham'd to own the truths of God, when they have been rendred in Pulpits, ſcandalous, blaſphemous, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, &amp;c. Sirs, it is your prayers that I ſtill deſire with me, and for me. I know no people under heaven that have more encouragement then you, to goe boldly to the Throne of grace, conſidering what reall &amp; full anſwers you have had of former ſeeking the Lord. Now the Lord more and more poure the ſpirit of grace and of ſupplication into your hearts, and fill you with wiſdome and ſpirituall underſtanding, and keep you ſincere, and without offence till the day of Chriſt; and thus prayes he who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Chriſtian Brother to ſerve you in the Goſpel <hi>JOHN CANNE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118389:5"/>
            <head>A Voice from the Temple, to the higher POWERS; Wherin is ſhewed, that it is, the Work and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Saints, to ſearch the Propheſies and Viſions of holy Scriptures, which concern the latter times: And that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> will reveal the knowledge of them, neere the end of their accompliſhment. And ſo much is here clearely proved, and the Objections to the contrary anſwered.</head>
            <p>THings muſt be removed, and taken off, from the place where they are, before they can be laid, and ſetled elſe where: That I may win others to the ſame opinion I am of, in the ſubject or matter I here plead for; I ſhall firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to anſwer ſuch <hi>Objections,</hi> which I conceive are moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1: <hi>When</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Acts 1.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>they were come together, they asked of him, ſaying, Lord, wilt thou at this time reſtore again the kingdome of Iſrael; And he ſaid unto them, it is not for you to know the times or the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his own power.</hi> If not for the Apoſtles to know, then not for others, who in gifts, place, and parts, are farre ſhort and inferiour to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. Becauſe it was neither convenient nor neceſſary for the Diſciples, (no, nor for any in that age) to know the Times; yet it doth not follow, that it was inexpedient or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary for others in ages after; Chriſt doth not ſay, <hi>It is not for any,</hi> or, <hi>it is not for others,</hi> but <hi>it is not for you to know;</hi> he means no way uſefull, or fit for them, as tending either to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or the Churches good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In ſaying, <hi>which the father hath put in his own power;</hi> he plainly intimates, that it ſhould be revealed and made known
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118389:6"/>in due time; and unto ſuch as he thought good. It was <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi>'s lot, to have his head cut off with his own ſword: this very ſcripture, if rightly weighed, is a moſt effectuall proof, to confute the very thing they bring it for.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As Chriſt told them, <hi>It was not for them to know the times:</hi> ſo he might have given them a reaſon for it; for the knowledge of the <hi>Time,</hi> concerning the <hi>reſtauration of the Kingdome to Iſrael,</hi> was then ſhut up, and ſealed, according to
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel,</hi> and not to be revealed, till towards or near the accompliſhment.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>But</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 24.37, 38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>as the dayes of Noah were, ſo ſhall alſo the coming of the Son of man be, for as in the dayes that were before the flood, they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, untill the day that Noah entred into the ark, and knew not, untill the flood came and took them all away, ſo ſhall alſo the coming of the Son of man be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I ſhall anſwer this ſcripture two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For the wicked and ungodly ſinners, the knowledge of the time was hid from them: and indeed, this is the thing which Chriſt in that place chiefly intends, in comparing the <hi>time of Noah</hi> with the latter times: for howſoever the prophane wretches then, neither knew, nor foreſaw the coming of the flood; yet <hi>Noah</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. 6, 7. and 7.4.</note> did: he (I ſay) both foreſaw and foretold the time of the old worlds deſtruction. It was indeed conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the wicked, becauſe it was to come upon them as a ſnare in the night, but revealed unto <hi>Noah</hi> for
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb. 11.7.</note> his own, and the Churches preſervation. <hi>Even thus</hi> (ſaith
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luk. 17 30.</note> Chriſt) <hi>ſhall it be in the day when the Son of man ſhall be revealed:</hi> that is, ſome ſhall know nothing of the <hi>times,</hi> but go on in their ignorance, and unbelief, as become
<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.34.</note> 
               <hi>ſcoffers, and walking after their own luſts, and ſaying, where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> and ſo periſh in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtruction; others on the other hand, by faith (like <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>) ſhall prepare an Ark, to the ſaving of their own ſouls.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As concerning the Saints, Chriſt doth not ſimply and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely deny unto them the knowledge of the time, for he knew that the time was to be revealed unto them,
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Dan. 12.4, 9, 10</note> near the end; but he denyeth it, onely to the Saints preſent, and far diſtant from the end, to whom it was not to be
<note n="(j)" place="margin">Dan. 12.4.10.</note> made known, as being unſeaſonable and not expedient, and would
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118389:6"/>have occaſioned rather hurt then good, Chriſt ſaith, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<note n="(l)" place="margin">John 7, 6, 10.</note> place, <hi>My time is not yet come;</hi> nevertheleſſe within a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while after he goes up to the feaſt: ſo concerning the godly (whether we reſpect the dayes of <hi>Daniel</hi> or <hi>Chriſt</hi>) the time then was not come that the propheſies of the <hi>End</hi> ſhould be opened to them; yet they ſhall be opened and made known to Saints near the finiſhing, and before their accompliſhment.</p>
            <p>Object. 3.
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mark 13.32.</note> 
               <hi>But of that day and hour knoweth no man, no not the angells which are in heaven, neither the Son but the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are ſeverall anſwers given; ſom, <hi>not as meere man:</hi> Others, though not the day and hour, yet the year might be known, both to Chriſt, angels and men. But to let theſe things paſſe, my anſwer is, Chriſt as <hi>the Son of man,</hi> knew it not, till he was aſcended and glorified; hence it is, that he is acknowledged
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 4, 5, 9</note> 
               <hi>worthy to take the book, and to open the Seals there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;</hi> mark the reaſon, <hi>For thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood:</hi> ſo then as
<note n="(o)" place="margin">Rev. 1.1</note> 
               <hi>God gave unto Jeſus Chriſt the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to ſhew unto his ſervants things which muſt ſhortly come to paſſe:</hi> ſo this is as a fruit of his ſufferings, riſing again, and fitting at the right hand of his father.</p>
            <p>And this is a point of marvellous conſequence (though little minded) for it is matter of encouragement to <hi>ask wiſdome of God,</hi> that we may underſtand <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>the book of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> what is meant by
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Dan. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>Time, times, and dividing of time,</hi> what by the
<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2.</note> 42 <hi>Moneths, the</hi> 1260 <hi>dayes,</hi> what by the
<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.18.</note> 
               <hi>number of the Beaſt, which is</hi> 666. <hi>and</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">Dan. 6.12, 6.</note> 
               <hi>how long it ſhall be to the end of theſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt by his death became <hi>worthy to open the Seals,</hi> that is, (with other things) purchaſed by his blood for us this great priviledge, <hi>to know the time and ſeaſons,</hi> and to make them known unto his Church and people. If it be a thing which a man owns, and hath a lawfull intereſt and right in it, he can ask it with the more boldneſſe and confidence, and doubts not but to have it. So here, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. 4. <hi>Many learned and godly men, diving and ſearching into theſe myſteries and hidden things, have been greatly miſtaken, and by their extravagances have loſt themſelves, which makes others warie and cautious how to meddle with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118389:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. By the ſame reaſon, other Scriptures are not to be ſearcht, for learned men have moſt corruptly and falſely interpreted them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Though it be aſſerted by us, that it is poſſible, needfull, yea, required to ſearch out the accommodation of the years, yet we do not ſay, every man (howbeit learned and godly) ſhall <hi>underſtand:</hi> for the Lord may do what he will with his own.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That many formerly have been miſtaken, it is not ſtrange, becauſe the time was uncertain in which they lived: the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation being reſerved (as I ſaid before) for the Saints of the laſt age. Beſides, that many, (I do not ſpeak of all) even in theſe our dayes, miſſe the mark, no marvell.</p>
            <p>For 1. Some of them
<note n="(t)" place="margin">Prov. 3.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>lean unto their own wiſdome,</hi> humane learning, arts, ſciences, authority of men: and ſeek not the Lord by faith and prayer, to have direction, light and counſell from him; and hence, (and juſtly too) is that verefied on them,
<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>profeſſing themſelves to be wiſe, they became fools.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 It is an uſuall thing with Scholars to follow one another right or wrong. The old Fathers (as they are call'd) apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many things to their times, which as then had no relation, others coming after, ſay the very ſame, and look no further, and ſo one leads another out of the way:</p>
            <p n="3">3 Another cauſe of many mens miſtake in the accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of years, is confounding one thing with another, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly ſetting down that firſt which ſhould be laſt, and laſt firſt: thus they appply promiſcuouſly to Jews and Gentiles, what ſhould be diſtinguiſhed, as proper but to one. Again, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh not between the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill State, as to the riſe and fall of both: cry up a preſent glorious condition of the Church, far before her warfare is accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for ſuch as are <hi>warie and cautious, how to meddle with the times.</hi> I ſhall ſay no more but thus. If a man towards the beginning of Harveſt, ſhould travell through the Countrie, from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>York,</hi> poſſibly then he would ſee very few <hi>Harveſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers</hi> in the fields but let him paſſe the ſame way a few weeks after, he ſhall ſee people every where at work, and every one his hands full. At preſent we are but at the beginning of the Harveſt, but I believe (and note it well) before one year is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118389:7"/>the Lord will ſend forth ſuch a multitude of <hi>labourers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Harveſt,</hi> as not a man that is come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and hath ſeperated himſelf from all the abominations thereof: but will make it his ſpeciall work to ſearch <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelaion,</hi> and diligently ſeek after the knowledge of the Times.</p>
            <p>Objection 5. <hi>This pretending to Inſpirations, Revelations, and the ſpirit of propheſie, is no other then what</hi> John <hi>of</hi> Leiden, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Rotman <hi>and</hi> Chipperdoling <hi>did, and ſo the</hi> Munſter <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereby multitudes were betrayed, and driven to Rebellion, and great miſchief and miſerie followed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. This is no other aſperſion and ſcandalons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, then hath been caſt by the enemies of the truth, upon all good men ever ſince, who have been zealouſly earneſt for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <p>But 2. Such as are godly, wiſe, or able to put a difference between lying propheſies, and fooliſh viſions, and a grace given unto Saints, to underſtand the mind of Jeſus Chriſt in holy Scriptures,
<note place="margin">2 John 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ye have an unction from the holy one, and ye ſhall know all things. To you</hi> (ſaith
<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> Chriſt) <hi>it is given to know the myſteries of the kingdome:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 25 14.</note> 
               <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him.</hi> Again,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Prov. 3.32.</note> 
               <hi>His ſecret is with the righteous.</hi> Are not theſe Goſpel promiſes, and Saints Priviledges, and attainable by the exerciſe and acts of faith.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pet. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>He that believeth on him, ſhall not be confounded.</hi> Becauſe the Spider turns many things into poyſon, is the honey, wormwood and gall, which the Bee makes?</p>
            <p n="3">3 I could ſhew in ſeverall particulars, how contrary (as light is to darkneſſe) the carriages and practiſes of the <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Impoſtors, (firſt and laſt) were, to what is either ſaid or done by the godly of this age, who are of my opinion, namely, <hi>that the propheſies of the laſt times ſhall be revealed unto Saints near the end.</hi> Let <hi>Sleidan</hi> (or any other) who hath written the Hiſtorie of <hi>Munſter,</hi> be peruſed by any impartiall Reader, and he ſhall not find any ground to frame a parralell, neither in reference to matter, manner, men. I have ſome thoughts, (ſeeing there is ſuch a noiſe of <hi>Munſter</hi>) ſhortly to diſcover the abſurdity, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and malice of ſuch people, who ſeek to diſgrace good men, and through their ſides to pierce the glorious work of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118389:8"/>God now begun amongſt us, by raking into the buſineſſe of <hi>Munſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is worth the obſerving, how ſutably Satan hath carried on his Deſigne to keep men in ignorance, ſupeſtition, and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and to hinder them from embracing the things belonging to their peace. Though he could never certainly and perfectly reach the knowledge of propheſies, as to the very time of their accompliſhment: yet knowing that ſuch and ſuch things ſhould come to paſſe, and having ſome conjecture near the time, his manner hath been beforehand, to corrupt the minds of the people (ſome way or other) with a prejudice againſt them, that ſo, when the thing it ſelf ſhould come to paſſe, men might neither believe nor receive the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus he raiſed up many <hi>falſe Chriſts,</hi> and why? that the true Chriſt might not be received when he came. So for this <hi>Munſter Buſineſſe.</hi> The Devill knew in the latter dayes, Tyrants and oppreſſors would be throw down, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian kingdom deſtroyed; good men and good things ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced: Now mark the craft of this wicked one; when the appointed time ſhould come, in which theſe things were to be fulfilled, to the end that men might not then believe: He ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up before hand a company of Seducers to beguile the ignorant and ſimple people: meerly, (I ſay) upon this account, that when the time ſhould come, that Tyranny and Oppreſſion ſhould be ſuppreſt, Babylon caſt down, righteouſneſſe exalted; this work might not finde acceptation among the people, he having (as I ſaid) poiſoned before hand the mindes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> by ſuggeſting <hi>Munſter</hi> and the effects of that buſineſſe: So then in ſhort, the ſumme is this, <hi>The Devill in cauſing that work at</hi> Munſter, <hi>intended that it ſhould be a ſnare to the people of this Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſpoken to the <hi>Objections;</hi> I come now to Arguments, to prove that <hi>the knowledge of the times</hi> is needfull, poſſible, yea re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and ought to be ſearcht; And ſo to juſtifie Gods people, (miniſters and others) who (by Faith, Prayer, Conference, meditation, reading) are now upon the work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe this is a part of the written word of God. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. and 9.25, 26. and 12.7.11.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2, 3. and 12.6.14. and 13.18. Now
<note n="(d)" place="margin">John 5.39.</note> Chriſt commandeth us <hi>to ſearch the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118389:8"/>the whole, and all, and not ſome part as we think good to pick and chuſe:
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our ledrning, that we through patience and comfort of the ſcriptures might have hope.</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Dan. 29 29</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe things which are revealed, belong unto us and to our children for ever.</hi> A ſervant being commanded to doe ſeverall things, if he do onely a part of them, what he thinks fit and beſt, (as eaſieſt) and not the reſt; the maſter will not be pleaſed: ſo here,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the knowledge of the Times, is part of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and thoſe good things to come, which the
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rev. 1.1</note> father gave unto his ſon, to ſend and ſhew unto his ſervants. Chriſt did not ſend the letter without the ſence: But intended, that it ſhould be known and underſtood; therefore the ſenſe and underſtanding is to be ſearcht.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſaid of the whole Propheſie, and conſequently of the Times therein contained:
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Rev. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this propheſie;</hi> I think no man takes it of an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and fruitleſſe reading and hearing, without under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: for ſurely, ſuch a hearing or reading
<note n="i" place="margin">Acts 8.30.</note> makes no man happy. Beſides it is ſuch a reading and hearing, as may be the rule and ground of practice: Hence it is added, <hi>and keep thoſe things which are written therein:</hi> Conſequently then, it muſt be a reading with underſtanding and knowledge. Obſerve hence the raſhneſſe of ſome Teachers, who ſeek to diſcourage Saints, from that work, unto which alone, is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the promiſe of bleſſedneſs. They will allow men to read the <hi>years</hi> and <hi>times</hi> in the text, but they muſt not ſeek for the underſtanding. Juſt for all the world, as to bid a man to catch at the ſhaddow, but with all charge him not to toucht or take the fruit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let Chriſts words be well obſerved, <hi>When</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 29 15</note> 
               <hi>yee therefore ſhall ſee the abomination of deſolation ſpoken of by</hi> Daniel <hi>the Prophet, ſtand in the holy place; who ſo readeth, let him underſtand:</hi> he hath reference, no doubt to <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. and 11.31. and 12, 11. where the times of the end are declared and Characterized: Chriſt here cals upon us, not for reading, but for <hi>underſtanding Daniels weeks, dayes, times.</hi> Now doth Chriſt bid us <hi>underſtand Daniel;</hi> yea, in his <hi>numbers,</hi> how dares any mortall creature, reproach
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118389:9"/>any for ſearching his Propheſies.
<note n="(l)" place="margin">Acts 4.2</note> 
               <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you, more then unto God, judge yee?</hi> A ſervant in not doing his duty, cannot be excuſed, but yet is more in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, when with all he ſhall ſmite his fellow ſervants for doing their duties. I leave the application to the Reader.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It muſt be granted, that the holy ſcripture, either holds forth a certain, and ſet time, and period of years; in reſpect of the breaking of the fourth Monarchy, the deſtruction of the Antichriſtian kingdome, the end of the Turkiſh Empire, the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, Chriſt taking the poſſeſſion of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and reigning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or not: If there be no time ſet, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time; for what uſe then are theſe Texts, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. and 9.25, 26, 27. and 12.11, 12. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.2, 3. and 12.6.14. If there be a time certain and fixt, then I would know; if nothing of the time is to be known, till after the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; how theſe and ſuch other ſcriptures, can be ſaid to be written for our learning and comfort? or, what benefit the Church and People of God have by having them written! <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> letter though he carried it with him in his boſome into the Councel, yet not knowing the contents, it profited him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. In the knowledge of the times, there lyes our comfort and ſafety; to have the words in our book, and no more, that helps not, though we have them with us ſtill in our boſome.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Daniel</hi> being commanded, <hi>to</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Dan. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſhut up the words, and ſeale the Book, even to the time of the end;</hi> afterwards, <hi>ſees</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">v. 5</note> 
               <hi>two, the one ſtanding on this ſide of the banck, and the other on that ſide of the banck of the river.</hi> Theſe <hi>two,</hi> I take to be Types, the one a <hi>Type</hi> of the Chriſtian Gentiles, the other of the Iewes; unto whom Ieſus Chriſt <hi>(the man clothed in linnen)</hi> will open the <hi>myſteries of the times,</hi> a little before the end.</p>
            <p>Three reaſons I have for this,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They both make enquiry, <hi>How</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>long ſhall it be to the end of theſe wonders?</hi> Our Bibles reade, <hi>and one ſaid to the man clothed.</hi> But the word <hi>(one)</hi> is not in the text; nor is there to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, for they ſpake both.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>man clothed in linnen</hi> (which was Chriſt)
<note n="(p)" place="margin">v. 7.</note> 
               <hi>holds up his right hand, and his left hand to heaven;</hi> wherefore both, and not one hand alone?
<note n="(q)" place="margin">10.5.</note> Becauſe here are two, one on his right hand,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118389:9"/>another on his left, and both to be informed</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are both anſwered, as to their queſtion, concerning the <hi>times.</hi> The <hi>Gentile type,</hi> hath his anſwer, v. 7. <hi>It ſhall be for a time, times, and an half:</hi> And the <hi>Jew type</hi> hath his anſwer, v. 11. <hi>From the time that the daily ſacrifice ſhall be taken away, and the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination that maketh deſolate ſet up; there ſhall be a thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ninety dayes.</hi> From this I gather, ſome litle time before the end, the Lord will unſeale the propheſies of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and reveal the <hi>times</hi> included, to ſome, both Iews and Gentiles. Thoſe great myſteries of the times, which have been hid, and lookt up from former ages, ſhall be clearly opened to them, and they ſhall know how long it will be before the Fourth Monarch be deſtroyed, <hi>the witneſſes ſlain, Euphrates dryed up,</hi> and <hi>Michael ſtand up for his people.</hi> And this they ſhall ſpeak out to the world, and not one <hi>jot</hi> of their words ſhall fail. You will ask it may be, what will men ſay to this? It will be with theſe men, as it was with <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s meſſengers, ſome <hi>laughed them to ſcorn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.11.</note> 
               <hi>and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cked them: Nevertheleſſe divers of Aſher, and Manaſſeh, and of Zebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lun, humbled themſelves, and came to Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. As the <hi>time of the end</hi> is neerer at hand, ſo the Propheſies, and conſequently the times included, are to be unſealed,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.9. Rev. 22.10. and 1.3.</note> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, revealed. In <hi>Daniel</hi> 12.7. when <hi>a time, times, and an half,</hi> was propoſed, and the Prophet profeſſing he underſtood it not, <hi>v.</hi> 8. an anſwer was given <hi>v.</hi> 9. that <hi>the words were ſealed up till the end;</hi> that is, untill the laſt time immediately before the end; as the phraſe is uſed, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 11.7. Therefore in the time immediately before the accompliſhment, theſe words are to be unſealed; that is, the meaning of them ſhall be known to Saints. Again this is further manifeſted by <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>Many ſhall be purified and made white and tryed; and none of the wicked ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand.</hi> So <hi>ver.</hi> 11. what they ſhould <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand at the time of the end,</hi> in particular, is there more fully expreſſed. <hi>And from the time</hi> (ſaith the Angel) <hi>that the daily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices ſhall be taken away; and the abomination that maketh deſolate ſet up, there ſhall be</hi> 1290. <hi>dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But wherefore hath the Lord denyed the knowledge of the times to his people in former ages; and will reveal it to Saints neer unto the end.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118389:10"/>
            <p> I might here ſay,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.26.</note> in the words of our Lord, <hi>Even ſo father, for ſo it ſeemeth good in thy ſight:</hi> But I Anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Gods adminiſtrations in the later Times, concerning a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Kingdom,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> to pluck up, and pull down, and to deſtroy it, will be ſuch as the inſtruments of the work, probably ſhall want former examples, and ordinary rules to walk by. Men at Sea having not the marks and directions, which travellers have on Land, need ſome other help to ſteer and order their courſe by: <hi>Gods way neer the end will be in the Sea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 77.19</note> 
               <hi>and his path in the great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> So that as the actions of ſome men ſhall be rare, unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary without preſident; ſo God will give them clear light in away ſuteable, that is, <hi>make them underſtand the times,</hi> and that it is now their proper work to act, ſo and ſo: in order to the fulfilling of the will and commandement of God, though the ſame (as the world judgeth) ſeem irrational, illegal, abſurd, deſtructive to Religion, Law, Liberty, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe latter times will be accompanied, with ſuch great deſtractions, confuſions, diviſions, as people will be at a loſſe, and ſo in darkneſſe, that they will not know what to doe, which way to take, nor how to diſpoſe of themſelves. <hi>Reader,</hi> note it; Gods marvelous work now in the world, will move ſo contrary to mens expectations and ſelf intereſt; as multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes ſhall fall off daily;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 60.2.</note> yea, ſome good men ſhall be offended, and left behinde; <hi>Darkneſſe ſhall, cover the earth, and groſſe dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the people:</hi> Nevertheleſſe, for the comfort and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>wiſe,</hi> the Lord ſhall ariſe upon them, and his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall be ſeen upon them; and by <hi>the underſtanding of the times,</hi> which they ſhall have, God will make them inſtrumentall, for the perfecting of the good work which he hath begun. Thus <hi>not by might,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>nor by power, but by my ſpirit, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As the knowledge of the end, hath been concealed from former Ages, to prevent ſecurity, and to ſtir men up unto watchfulneſſe;
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.42. Mar. 13.35 Luk. 12.40</note> as our Saviour expreſly ſhews; ſo it is to be revealed to this laſt Age, to move men to repentance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life; that they ſhould forſake all unrighteouſneſs, guile, diſſimulation, ſelf-ſeeking; <hi>Doe juſtice, love mercy, loſe the bonds of wickedneſſe, undoe the heavy burdens, and let the oppreſſed go free, and break every yoke.</hi> If a man fall into a pit, or ſnare,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118389:10"/>whereof he was before told and warned, he vexeth and grieves the more. When corrupt and deceitfull men ſhall ſee the very thing come to paſſe upon them, which before <hi>in the word of the Lord,</hi> was told them: namely within ſuch a time, if they turn not from their evill wayes, and make their wayes and their doings good, the Lord will pluck them out of their dwelling places, lay them aſide, break their power to pieces: Lord, what a torment and vexation this will be to them: that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding warned and admoniſhed as from God, they ſhould yet harden and hearten themſelves to their own deſtruction.
<note place="margin">Prov. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>How have I hated inſtruction, and my heart deſpiſed reproof? and have not obeyd the voice of my teachers, nor inclined mine ear to them that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 For this cauſe likewiſe will the Lord have the book now opened, <hi>viz.</hi> to advance the honour and holineſſe of his bleſſed word: we are in an age wherein moſt things are queſtioned: not only water-Baptiſme, and whether there be a true Church: but whether there be a true God, a true Chriſt, a true Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now as this is atime, wherein Satan appears againſt the holy Scriptures, and the truths therein contained, more violently and blaſphemouſly then ever heretofore: ſo I confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, and will abide by it, that the Lord will now ariſe and appear for the vindication of the holy Scriptures, more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and eminently then ever: And wherein can the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of them be more advanced? the truths in them more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted? the contemners of them more aſhamed and ſilenced, then that <hi>the wiſe ſhould underſtand.</hi> For what Athieſt will not bluſh, and be confounded, when he ſhall moſt evidently ſee ſuch things come to paſſe this year and the next, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, till the year, 1770. as was foretold: And that in order to the fulfilling of propheſies and viſions, recorded, ſome fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years, others, two thouſand years before, and more:</p>
            <p>Having proved by ſeverall Arguments, that <hi>the knowledge of the times,</hi> is poſſible, and ought to be ſearched, and wherefore the ſame (though concealed from former ages) is to be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the laſt age. I come now to the <hi>Propheſies</hi> themſelves. In <hi>Daniel</hi> I find five ſpeciall propheſies, in reference to the <hi>time
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118389:11"/>of the end, Chap.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.24, 25, 26, 27. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.7, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>The three firſt concern the Chriſtian Gentiles, the two latter the Jews; and in them are comprehended all the works of both: that is, when thoſe years are expired, then their whole warfare ſhall be accompliſhed, and they ſhall be no more two, but one; and one ſhepherd ſhall be ſet over them. Howſoever I intend to ſet forth theſe things, more at large in another Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; yet ſomething I will ſpeak now, as to the times, both of the Gentiles, and of the Jews. And firſt to that place in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill a time, and times, and dividing of times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Scripture we find <hi>time,</hi> to be taken for dayes, as <hi>Dan</hi> 4. comparing <hi>v.</hi> 16. with 34. By <hi>dayes,</hi> years are to be underſtood. <hi>Your children ſhall wander in the wilderneſſe forty dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 14.33, 34. Ezek. 4.6</note> 
               <hi>each day for a year.</hi> Again, <hi>Thou ſhalt bear their iniquity forty dayes, and I have appointed thee each day for a year.</hi> In propheticall uſe, <hi>a day,</hi> that is, a <hi>year,</hi> containeth 360 <hi>dayes,</hi> or years. This <hi>Daniel</hi> calls <hi>a time.</hi> The word <hi>times,</hi> ſignifies ſo much more, that is, 720 <hi>years. The dividing of time</hi> is, 180 <hi>dayes,</hi> or <hi>years,</hi> the whole put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, makes 1260 <hi>years:</hi> and ſo much, the ſpirit of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declares in <hi>Rev</hi> 12. where <hi>a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore dayes,</hi> v. 6. is ſaid to be, <hi>a time, and times, and half a time v.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>Before we come to the accommodation of theſe years, we are to ſpeak of the <hi>ten horns,</hi> and the <hi>little horn:</hi> firſt of their riſe, then their fall; that is, their beginning and ending: For their riſe or beginning, it is to be underſtood, either as hid and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret or more plain and open. Theſe <hi>ten horns,</hi> I underſtand to be the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> diſſolved into ten parts or Kingdoms. In the enumeration of them, ſome produce them thus. <hi>Brittany, France, Germany, Spain, Italy, Africa, Aſia, Graecia, Syria,</hi> and <hi>Egypt.</hi> I ſhall ſet down what to me, is moſt probable. 1. The kingdom of the <hi>Brittains,</hi> 2 of the <hi>Saxons</hi> both in <hi>Brittany,</hi> 3 of the kingdom of the <hi>Franks,</hi> 4 of the <hi>Burgundians,</hi> both in <hi>France,</hi> 5 The kingdome of the Weſt Gothes, in the Southern part of <hi>France,</hi> and part of <hi>Spain,</hi> 6. the <hi>Sueves</hi> and <hi>Alanes</hi> in part of <hi>Spain,</hi> 7 the Kingdome of the <hi>Vandals</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> a little before in <hi>Spain,</hi> 8. The Alemanes <hi>in Rhaetia,</hi> and <hi>Noricum,</hi> Provinces of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi> 9 the Kingdome of the Eaſt <hi>Goths</hi> in <hi>Ponnonia,</hi> a little
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118389:11"/>before in <hi>Italy,</hi> Laſtly the Kingdome of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> in the remnant of the Empire. Though this Decharchicall diviſion doth not continue, yet that it was ſo at firſt, is apparent by Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>For their Riſe, which was obſcure and dark,
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.8.</note> which gave <hi>Daniel</hi> occaſion to <hi>conſider the hornes,</hi> (as being ſo low and ſhort that he could ſcarce perceive them) this was about the <hi>year of our Lord,</hi> 388. It is true, the fall of the Empire was by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and it was 40 <hi>years</hi> after, or more, before the ſame was effectually diſſolved. Nevertheleſſe about this time, to wit the <hi>year</hi> 388. thoſe <hi>horns</hi> did appear, though obſcure, and little, (as I ſaid before) in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12. <hi>The horns which thou ſaweſt, are ten Kings, which have received no Kingdome as yet, but receive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at Kings one hour with the Beaſt,</hi> that is, they had not at firſt a Soveraignty, Majeſty, Power, Priviledges, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards they poſſeſt, and were confirmed in. Now adde un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 388. (which was the time of the riſe <hi>of the ten horns,</hi> and the Romane Empire its beginning to diſſolve) <hi>Daniels number,</hi> namely, 1260. and it extendeth to the year of Chriſt, 1648.</p>
            <p>This <hi>year,</hi> to wit the <hi>year</hi> 1648. do I affirm with much aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, was the <hi>time,</hi> when <hi>the Thrones were ſet, and the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of dayes did ſit,</hi> as is expreſſed in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10. Here began the Lord God Almighty, to call Kings and Kingdomes to an account, to caſt down the mighty from their ſeats, to cut off the ſpirit of Princes, and to be terrible unto the Kings of the earth. And this work goes forward ſtill, and ſhall prevail and proſper, to the utter breaking and deſtroying of the fourth <hi>Monarch,</hi> or <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> diſſolved into <hi>ten Kingdomes:</hi> And the <hi>little horn,</hi> that is, the Antichriſtian State, and Kingdom likewiſe.</p>
            <p>I know it will be expected, that I give ſome reaſons for what is here aſſerted, eſpecially, it being delivered with ſo much confidence: This I ſhall willingly do.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Howſoever our <hi>Chronicles</hi> give the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> ſome kind of intereſt and title to the <hi>Brittains,</hi> till the year 440. yet it was rather in name then in thing; For after the year 388. the <hi>Romanes</hi> never exerciſed that power here which they did before, onely now and then (and that upon earneſt intreaty) they ſent hither ſome relief againſt the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts,</hi> &amp; having)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118389:12"/>done their work, immediately returned back again, leaving the <hi>Brittons</hi> to themſelves. Thus their Hiſtories ſerve to give ſome light unto <hi>Daniels viſions</hi> concerning the <hi>Times.</hi> Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their thoughts were not at all carried out on ſuch a thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Who ever was the laſt, certain it is, that <hi>England</hi> was the firſt of the <hi>ten horns,</hi> and therefore here firſt were the throns ſet up, and judgement given upon the King and Kingdome. <hi>True and righteous are his judgements.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The high Court of Juſtice,</hi> which was erected in the <hi>Year</hi> 1648. before which, the laſt of our kings had his tryal and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, was no other, then that <hi>throne of God,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10. I doe not confine the <hi>thrones</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the ſitting of the <hi>ancient of dayes,</hi> unto <hi>England.</hi> For I know the Lord will have his <hi>thrones</hi> ſpeedily ſet up in other kingdomes; as <hi>France, Spain, Denmark, &amp;c.</hi> and as he proceeded here, ſo he will do there, <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICATORY</hi> againſt Kings and Kingdomes. But to the point in hand, What was done by the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>High court of Juſtice,</hi> in taking away the king, and changing (in part) the form of Government, was no other then a fulfilling of that propheſie in <hi>Daniel.</hi> Not that our Stateſmen thought ſo, or ſo intended; but God did put it in their hearts to fulfill his will, that it ſhould be ſo. And whereas this thing, not being before heard of, poſſibly will be ſleighted; therefore for prevention, I ſhall let the Reader know my reaſons for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was given by the Angel unto <hi>Daniel,</hi> that the continuance of the <hi>ten horns</hi> or <hi>kingdomes,</hi> after their riſe and appearing, ſhould be onely 1260 <hi>years, untill the thrones were ſet.</hi> In the year 1648. that term expired, for againſt the <hi>Engliſh horn,</hi> the <hi>Ancient of dayes came,</hi> and gave judgement. So that it muſt neceſſary fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, in the year 388. the <hi>Brittons</hi> became one of the <hi>horns.</hi> We need not be beholding to humane hiſtories, where the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is clear, notwithſtanding in this point, our <hi>Chronocles</hi> (as I ſaid even now) agree with <hi>Daniel,</hi> as to the riſe of the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh horn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From accommodating the years, let us conſider the <hi>work</hi> and <hi>thrones:</hi> For the <hi>work</hi> firſt, It is true, in all ages before this, Kings have been depoſed, impriſoned, put to death; but it was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118389:12"/>rather mans ſiting on the throne, then <hi>the Ancient of dayes;</hi> for what they did, was only cutting off one <hi>horn</hi> or Tyrant, and ſetting another up: whereas root and branch was here taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And this is the proper work of <hi>Thrones, to change the times &amp; ſeaſons:</hi> diſſolve foundations, and remove former Pillars, I ſay abſolutely, and utterly to break in pieces and conſume the <hi>ten horns</hi> or <hi>kingdomes; their places muſt not be found any more upon earth:</hi> But a new form of government, is to be conſtituted and ſet up.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Ancient of dayes</hi> hath <hi>ſet up his throne in England,</hi> I am further confirmed, by the happy diſſolution of the late Parliament; really, I have wondred, that the Lord ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch men, ſo long to prophane his throne;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.14.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtice and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are the habitation of thy throne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſateſt in the throne doing right,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 9.4.</p>
            <p>I know many are in darkneſſe concerning this great change, &amp; not able to apprehend the true ground and cauſe therof, they run, ſome into miſtakes, ſome into diſcontents, ſome into rage and fury. For the ſatisfying therefore of ſuch people, who deſire to eye God, and his hand which is lifted up; I ſhall ſhew what is the true cauſe, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> was diſſolved.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ancient of days,</hi> having ſet up his <hi>throne</hi> amongſt us (from which he will ſpeak to, and plead with the Nations round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) was pleaſed to honour thoſe men formerly in place, as to admit them, to ſit upon his Throne: And becauſe (like <hi>Jehu</hi>) they did well in executing that which was right in the eyes of the Lord, and did unto the houſe of <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> all that was in his heart; the Lord ſuffered them many years to ſit <hi>on the throne of England:</hi> but taking no heed to walk in the law of the Lord God of Iſrael, but <hi>flying upon the ſpoile,</hi> and giving countenance and encouragement to the ſins of <hi>Jeroboam:</hi> God at laſt rejected them, as he did <hi>Saul.</hi> And for this cauſe, raiſed up the <hi>Generall;</hi> I ſay, for the <hi>Thrones ſake,</hi> that they might be no longer polluted and prophaned by ſuch a generation of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt men. And had not the Generall done what he did, to have the Thrones purged from that droſſe and filth, which clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereto. I know not how he could have anſwered God, for that power, and truſt which he hath put into his hands.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118389:13"/>
            <p> And here (by the way) let me ſpeak a word unto ſuch as ſhall ſit next upon this <hi>Throne;</hi> I would have men conſider well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand what they doe. Its Gods own throne, and to ſpeake comparatively, it is the onely Civil Throne, he hath now in the world; By it he will doe mighty and terrible things: And therefore ſuch as are not for Chriſt, and for the carrying on of his deſigne in the world, he will lay them aſide, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And ſet ſuch up, as ſhall poure out the laſt Vials quickly upon Monarchs, and the Antichriſtian Kingdome.</p>
            <p>One thing more, I ſhall add, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10. It is ſaid, <hi>And the fift Angel poured out his vial upon the throne of the Beaſt</hi> (ſo the Greek hath it, <hi>throne,</hi> not <hi>ſeat</hi>) <hi>and his kingdome was full of darkneſſe:</hi> By the <hi>throne of the Beaſt,</hi> I underſtand the ten <hi>horns,</hi> that is, the States and Kingdomes of the World, which gave authority and power to the <hi>Beaſt.</hi> By <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> I doe not underſtand, (at leaſt not chiefly) that which is ſpirituall, as in reference to their Errors, Superſtitions, Idolatries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſo that <hi>kingdome was full of darkneſſe</hi> before: but it is meant of amazement and diſtraction: not knowing what to doe, nor ſeeing any way how to come out. For application to the thing in hand; after the death of the late king, his throne and kingdom periſhing under the <hi>fifth Vial:</hi> how were people then generally at their wits end? in ſuch <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> as they fell one upon another. So upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving of this <hi>Parliament</hi> (which was ſo degenerate, as it lookt more like the <hi>throne of the beaſt,</hi> then Gods throne) what a thick darkneſſe is now gone over men, as if an Angel had ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them with blindneſſe, as were the <hi>Sodomites.</hi> And this you muſt expect ſtill along, that as <hi>Thrones, States, Powers,</hi> are broken to pieces: ſo confuſion, deſtraction, and darkneſſe will ever fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; eſpecially among hypocrites, time-ſervers, and the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians. <hi>None of the wicked ſhall underſtand, but the wiſe ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand,</hi> Dan. 10.12.</p>
            <p>And therefore, for the <hi>Generall,</hi> and ſuch with him, whom the Lord uſed as ſeaſonable and good inſtruments to diſſolve the late Parliament; here may they ſee a divine ſtamp and chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter upon their work, even Gods owning both it and them; namely by this <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> which is fallen upon the children of this world. Had the Antichriſtians approved it: had thoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118389:13"/>which have enriched themſelves (Miniſters and others) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the late Parliament, appeared in it, and for it, had our Judges and Lawyers cryed it up, <hi>Law, Law;</hi> had the Clergy given thanks for it. In a word, had the people through the whole Nation ſent in their approbation and conſent to it, a man might very well have queſtioned the worke, whether it were of God, or no. But conſidering upon the breaking of this Throne, what darkneſs followed in Prieſt, in People: It is moſt evident and cleare, that it was not <hi>Gods Throne,</hi> but mans rather, and for this end thrown down, that the <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of dayes</hi> may have his <hi>throne</hi> ſet up, and he ſit againe moſt gloriouſly amongſt us.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>ten hornes,</hi> I come now to the <hi>Little horne,</hi> who is ſaid <hi>to weare out the Saints of the moſt high, and thinke to change times and lawes.</hi> I know it is the common received opinion, that <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> is here meant. Why I take it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, not <hi>Antiochus,</hi> but <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or the <hi>Antichriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> to be here underſtood, my Reaſons are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as affirme <hi>Antiochus</hi> to be the <hi>little horne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 7.8.20.</note> do reckon him as one of the <hi>ten:</hi> But it is expreſly ſaid, that he came up after them, and is <hi>beſides them,</hi> and <hi>another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.9. 'tis ſaid, that this <hi>little horn waxed great,</hi> grew ſtatelier then the reſt, and over-topt the former <hi>Beaſts</hi> and <hi>hornes:</hi> Now all know, that know any thing of the Hiſtory of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> that this is neither ſo, nor ſo; for <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Magnus</hi> was greater, and more powerfull by farre then he.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8.</note> For the <hi>three hornes</hi> which the <hi>little horne</hi> is ſaid to <hi>plucke up by the roots:</hi> as Writers cannot agree who they were, ſo it is apparant that this <hi>Antiochus</hi> never did the things which they do aſcribe unto him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the words, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill a time, times, and dividing of time,</hi> they cannot be applyed to the rage of <hi>Antiochus</hi> againſt the Saints, nor with his actions and proceedings againſt the <hi>Iews,</hi> as is moſt apparent, by comparing the phraſe, with other Texts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. and 12.6.14.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If <hi>Antiochus</hi> had been the <hi>little horne,</hi> then after his death ſhould the kingdome of the <hi>Seleucidae</hi> immediately have been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118389:14"/>given up to the <hi>Jews.</hi> For it is as clear as the ſun at noon-day, upon the deſtruction of the <hi>little horn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 7.21, 22.</note> the Saints immediately poſſeſſe his Kingdom. But it is well known, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> by the deſtruction of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> had no reſtauration, but continued ſtill after that in bondage, and ſubject to the <hi>Roman</hi> power.</p>
            <p>To apply this (as many doe) to the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, and ſo of a ſpirituall Kingdome, and liberty, is moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and groundleſſe. For not only was Chriſt born two or three hundred years after, but it is quite beſide the ſcope and purpoſe of the place, as follows.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. it is ſaid, <hi>And the kingdome, and dominion, and the greatneſſe of the Kingdome under the whole heaven ſhall be given to the people of the moſt high.</hi> Obſerve here, whatſoever <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Dominion, Greatneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and the <hi>little horne</hi> had, upon their deſtruction, the Saints ſhall have the ſame. Now this cannot be underſtood of a ſpirituall Kingdome: For, 1. the Saints had ever that, and Chriſt ſpiritually alwayes reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over them.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Note.</note> The <hi>Beaſt</hi> and the <hi>little horne</hi> never had a ſpiritual King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which ſhould be given up to the Saints after their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: And therefore the <hi>Kingdome, and dominion, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> poſſeſſed firſt by the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>little horne,</hi> and after their ruine to be given to the Saints, muſt needs be civill and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall.</p>
            <p>Why I take the <hi>little horn</hi> to be <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> my reaſon for it is this: It is generally held, that the holy Scripture is beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by comparing pararall Texts. Now this is cleare, whatſoever in <hi>Daniel</hi> is ſpoken of the <hi>little horne,</hi> the ſame in other Scripture is applyed to Antichriſt. For example,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As the <hi>little horne</hi> is conjoyned with the <hi>ten hornes, Dan.</hi> 7.7, 8.20.24. ſo is <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with the <hi>ten hornes, Revel.</hi> 17.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such practiſes and proceedings, as in <hi>Daniel</hi> are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the <hi>little horne,</hi> the very ſame are applyed to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> in other Texts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That hee ſhall <hi>ſpeake great ſwelling words againſt God,</hi> Dan. 7.25. The ſame is ſaid of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> Rev. 13.5, 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he ſhall advance himſelfe againſt the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118389:14"/>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.20. &amp; 8.25. So <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſaid of the <hi>little horne,</hi> that <hi>he ſhall change times</hi> and <hi>lawes,</hi> Dan. 7.25. So <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is called the <hi>lawleſſe one,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>little horne</hi> is ſaid <hi>to make war againſt the Saints,</hi> Dan. 7.21.25. So <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> Revel. 13.7.</p>
            <p>Againe, for the time alotted to the <hi>little horne,</hi> and the ſpace of his tyranny, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. it is the ſame expreſly with <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, Rev.</hi> 12.6.14 &amp; 13.5.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for the end and deſtruction of them both, compare <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10.11. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.21. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. with 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p>Thus having proved the <hi>little horne</hi> to be <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> I come now to ſome particulars concerning his riſe and fall.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.20.</note> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Daniel,</hi> he ſeems to be af er the <hi>ten hornes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Yet <hi>John</hi> ſaith, the <hi>ten hornes receive power as Kings one houre with the beaſt.</hi> The places are eaſily reconciled, as thus: Their riſe was toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no difference or diſtance in point of Time: but <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> is ſaid to be after the <hi>ten hornes,</hi> as receiving from them his power, dominion, juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Againe, for the Readers better underſtanding, as to the riſe and fall of the <hi>little horne,</hi> there are two things I would have him obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>little horne</hi> is to be conſidered as the Kingdom of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and as the members, or worſhippers of the <hi>Beaſt: By the Kingdome of the Beaſt,</hi> I underſtand him, as <hi>changing times and lawes:</hi> By the <hi>members,</hi> as <hi>making warre againſt the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak of the <hi>little horne,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> I doe not meane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Pope, or any ſucceſſion that way, but I meane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Kingdome.</hi> It is true, the Pope is a member of that body, but he is not the body.</p>
            <p>Againe, I do not here intend alone the <hi>Church, Miniſtery, worſhip, and government of Rome.</hi> But I include all falſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Miniſtries, Formes, Ordinances, Inſtitutions, brought in by men: whatſoever in the worſhip of God is beſides, or contrary to the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt. All this, whether in <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> make up this Antichriſtian Kingdome, as that in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118389:15"/>
            <p> Now for the riſe or beginning of this <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdom;</hi> Firſt, as it was obſcure and darke, ſo it had its beginning in the <hi>yeare of our Lord,</hi> 400. to this adde 1260. and it goes to the yeare 1660. And here is <hi>the time of the end,</hi> concerning the whole Antichriſtian kingdome; for further, and beyond this time, I believe it ſhall not extend. I do not ſay, that the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians, or members of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ſhall periſh now, or before; for I hold the contrary, that after their Kingdome is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, many of them ſhall remain, and attempt moſt horrible and cruell actions:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1.</note> but for the State it ſelfe, that <hi>ſhall be found no more at all</hi> after the year 1660. This the Angel calls the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great whore.</hi> Why <hi>Judgement?</hi> becauſe <hi>Thrones ſhall be ſet, and the ancient of dayes ſhall ſit:</hi> And look, as by a law, Kings and Kingly power ſhall be caſt out from the Nations, ſo will the Lord raiſe up men zealous of his glory, who ſhall publiquely give Judgment agaiſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> that it remaine for ever in the duſt.</p>
            <p>Before I come to ſhew my reaſons for the time which I have aſſerted, I ſhall commend theſe three things to the Reader.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How I underſtand that place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.2. where <hi>the mighty Angell, ſets his right foot upon the ſea, and his left foot upon the earth.</hi> As by the Angel Chriſt is meant, ſo as he ſtands, it is upon the two perſecuting powers in the world, the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and the temporal: <hi>His right foot is upon the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Note how they call it the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Biſhops Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſea;</hi> you know the <hi>ſpirituall power</hi> went ever before the temporall: Hence they uſed to ſay, the <hi>Lords ſpirituall,</hi> and the <hi>Lords temporall. And his left foote on the earth;</hi> that is, on the Kings and Kingdomes of the earth. So then my opinion is, that theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owers Chriſt will cruſh under his feet together, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> time. There was a truth in that ſaying, <hi>no Biſhop, no Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> event made it true: and <hi>welfare a good token.</hi> So now, as the reliques of Monarchy which remaine yet with us ſhall bemoved, ſo will the remainers of the Antichriſtian Kingdome be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with them. As Monarchy falls, ſo falls Antichriſtime: When no foot-ſteps of Monarchy remaine, nothing then will ſtand of the Antichriſtian kingdome, which came in with it, and hath ever ſince been upheld and ſupported by it.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe a long time, I never expected any good from the late Parliament: For I plainly ſaw, they had no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118389:15"/>to glorifie God (in the fulfilling of his will) to the roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of the remnants either of Monarchy or Antichiſtime: but rather ſought to oppreſſe the bodies and ſouls of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under the heavy burthens of them both.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou art to take notice (Reader) that as the the <hi>thrones</hi> were firſt ſet up in <hi>England</hi> to arreign <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and to pluck up by the root that tyrannicall power which ſtood in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Jeſus Chriſt, and to avenge the blood of his Saints up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: Even ſo (as ſutable to it) here with us will begin his great work (by the <hi>Thornes</hi>) againſt the kingdome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, for the totall extirpation thereof. For howſoever I ſaid before, that the Antichriſtian State (as Church, Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Worſhip, Government) ſhall be wholly deſtroyed before the yeare 1660. Yet I am of opinion, in reſpect of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> before one halfe of that time is expired, the Supream Authority of this Nation will effectually finiſh that work.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.6.</note> 
               <hi>If it be marvellous in the eyes of the remnant of this people in theſe dayes: ſhould it be marvellous in my eyes, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What progreſſe in this worke they will make, who ſhall come next in place, I cannot tell: but this I muſt tell them; the great buſineſſe which the Lord hath for the <hi>higher Powers</hi> of this Common-wealth now to doe, it is in order to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of thoſe Propheſies which relate to the preſent time: and if they do not look now after this, and honour God in a conſcientious and faithfull diſcharge thereof; the Lord will not look after them, nor honour them, but lay them aſide, and let their names rot, as others before: And therefore if my counſell may be acceptable unto them; when any ſhall make adreſſes to them <hi>for Peace with Babylon,</hi> let them make anſwer in his words, <hi>What peace, ſo long as the whoredomes of Jezabel and her witch-crafts are ſo many?</hi> What Peace, ſo long as the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Monarch is not broken to pieces, and conſumed? I would willingly know how men can enter into a league, as to ſit ſtill, and ſuffer ſuch things to ſtand, againſt which the Lord cals them forth to warre, and to deſtroy from the face of the earth. <hi>I have commanded my ſanctified ones;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>I have alſo called my mighty ones for mine anger, even them that rejoyce in my highneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118389:16"/> 3. As Chriſt will cruſh both powers at once, and thus by the <hi>Thrones:</hi> ſo there will be a ſpeciall opening of his minde unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, whereby to know both their worke and time. As men formerly have obſerved Providence, ſo in the later age,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.2.</note> they ſhall underſtand Propheſies, and act in order to them, and to the accompliſhment of them. <hi>Declare yee among the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and publiſh and ſet up a ſtandard, publiſh and conceale not, ſay Babylon is taken.</hi> The knowledge of <hi>the time of the end</hi> will be ſo cleare and certain to ſome men now ſhortly in power and place, as they will publickly declare upon what account they act, namely as being choſen and called of God <hi>to execute the vengeance of the Lord upon Babylon.</hi> Moreover the difference ſhall not be (as heretofore) about <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum;</hi> for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, greatneſſe, enlargement of Dominion, and ſuch world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpects, but better bottomed: it ſhall be for Chriſt, <hi>his Crown and dignity,</hi> and that righteouſneſſe and truth may be exalted in the earth.</p>
            <p>For the Reaſons now, why I ſay the Antichriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (as it is the <hi>little horne</hi>) had its riſe about the year 400.</p>
            <p n="1">1. About this time they began to open a paſſage to their pretended Supremacy, as giving to <hi>the Church of Rome</hi> the title of the <hi>Firmament of all Biſhops, and top of all Churches,</hi> and that <hi>without the privacie of the Sea Apoſtolique,</hi> that is, <hi>of the Primate, none might preſume to ordaine a Biſhop, and that the Cenſures of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in all cauſes of moment, was to be referred to the audience of the Biſhop of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. About this time the <hi>little horne</hi> began to give check to Emperours and Kings, and to exalt himſelfe above the Civill Magiſtrate, in ſeverall particulars.</p>
            <p n="3">3. About this time they brought in many beaſtly lies, and ſuperſtitious vanities, confirming them by Councels, whereby Gods commandements were made of none effect.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is clear to me by other Scriptures (which I have not now time to open) that the time alotted to the Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Kingdome ſhall not paſſe the yeare 1660. Now being to continue from firſt to laſt, 1260. years, it muſt needs be, that his beginning was in the yeare 400. as I ſaid before.</p>
            <p>Here I muſt againe put the <hi>Reader</hi> in mind, that howſoever
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118389:16"/>
               <hi>the vile perſon</hi> mentioned, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. be the ſame here with the <hi>little horne,</hi> that is, the Antichriſtian Kingdome. Yet they are to be differenced in point of time, as not having their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and riſe together.</p>
            <p>In this place the Antichriſtian Kingdome is the <hi>little horne,</hi> but not the <hi>vile perſon,</hi> becauſe the baſeneſſe and abhominable iniquity of that State, was not ſo high and full as afterwards it was, and appeared to the world: and therefore then rightly called the <hi>vile perſon,</hi> and not the <hi>little horne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed, from the <hi>State-plague,</hi> I come to what is perſonall. After the Eccleſiaſticall Kingdom ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>Every plant which the heavenly father hath not planted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13.</note> 
               <hi>rooted up,</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtians,</hi> and <hi>worſhippers of the Beaſt</hi> will remaine, and in as much blindneſſe, and hardneſſe of heart as before. And ſo much appears, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.9.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where <hi>the Kings of the Earth and the Merchants</hi> are brought in <hi>weeping and wailing,</hi> when they <hi>ſee the ſmoake of the burning.</hi> Now to finde out the <hi>time of the end,</hi> concerning theſe mens deſtruction, we muſt enquire after the firſt warr which the worſhiprers of the Beaſt made againſt the Saints.</p>
            <p>Twice the woman is ſaid <hi>to flye into the wilderneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6.14.</note> And <hi>two warres</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> made againſt her: the former, when that State was the <hi>little horne:</hi> the later, when it was the <hi>vile perſon.</hi> Of the firſt now I intend only to ſpeak: Although the later, which was againſt the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> be more memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, both for the cruelty and continuance of it, and will give much light to the matter I have in hand: and therefore I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſe (by the good hand of God aſſiſting me) ſhortly to ſet it forth.</p>
            <p>The firſt warre (I finde) made againſt the people of God by the Antichriſtians, was <hi>in the yeare</hi> 406. About that time wee read of a people called <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who by the <hi>Antichriſtian Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> and others, were held Schiſmaticks, Hereticks, Blaſphemers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and no otherwiſe proceeded againſt, and perſecuted, then if they had beene indeed moſt wicked people. Others after them (ſpecially the Prieſts) even to this day (as Carriers horſes) follow the ſteps of their fore-fathers, not taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice who were their accuſers, nor the particulars whereof they were accuſed.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118389:17"/>
            <p> Theſe <hi>Donatiſts</hi> (by what doth appeare in the writings of their adverſaries) were honeſt men, <hi>ſound in the faith,</hi> and ſuffered very much for the Truth ſake. Concerning their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, howſoever we have them not, but as reported, and ſet downe by their Enemies (who no doubt made things as bad as they could) yet we ſhall take them as from them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They denyed the <hi>publique Aſſemblies;</hi> that is, the <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> of the Papiſts, as not being the Churches of Chriſt rightly conſtituted, and ſeparated from them, becauſe of the leaven and abhominations therein.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They refuſed to ſubmit to that power and form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which the <hi>little horne</hi> had deviſed and ſet up.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They held that the Sacraments were no otherwiſe holy, then as they were given and taken by holy men.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It was their opinion that the Magiſtrate ſhould not compell mens conſciences, not force unto acts of Religion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are accuſed, as being <hi>Millenaries,</hi> that is, did believe and teach that Jeſus Chriſt in his humane nature, ſhould perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally reign upon Earth.</p>
            <p>I know other things are laid to their charge, but ſo impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable; yea impoſſible (if ſuch particulars as theſe were their Tenets) as their Enemies might have been aſham'd to put them gether; and others ſince more aſham'd of their ignorance and ſimplicity, as not to ſee how ridiculous, abſurd, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory the old Popiſh Fathers are (<hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf) in the Story which they have left behind them, concerning the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſts.</hi> But to proceed.</p>
            <p>Againſt theſe good men (in whom began the witneſſes that ſhould <hi>propheſie a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in ſack-cloath</hi>) warred the <hi>little horne</hi> (in <hi>his worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi>) by Canons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3.</note> Councels, Emperiall Edicts, &amp;c. to the ſhedding of much innocent and precious blood: And this was (as I ſaid before) in the <hi>yeare</hi> 406. to which 1260. yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing added, it comes to the <hi>yeare</hi> 1666. and to <hi>the number of the Beaſt</hi> 666. So then in briefe, my opinion is this: As the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian State</hi> ſhal be deſtroyed before or by the year 1660. and all that fulfilled which is ſet down, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. ſo, not beyond the yeare 1666. ſhall the <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> themſelves, and <hi>worſhippers
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118389:17"/>of the Beaſt, eſcape the vengeance of the Lord, and of his Temple.</hi> But either <hi>by repentance from dead workes,</hi> come in, and put themſelves under the glorious Scepter of Jeſus Chriſt; or caſt into the great Wine-preſſe of the wrath of God, and ſo that fulfilled, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. And here the Lord wil put an end, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to all the troubles of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Churches, not to goe beyond, or further then the <hi>yeare</hi> 1666. After that time they ſhall be called to <hi>the marriage ſupper of the Lamb,</hi> and ſing <hi>Allelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah, ſalvation, and glory, and honour, and power unto the Lord God: Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah, for the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done for this time with the firſt Propheſie. For the ſecond which concerns the 70. <hi>weeks,</hi> I know 'tis generally applyed to the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, and to his death and ſufferings: but I underſtand it otherwiſe, as being one of the choiſeſt and cleareſt Propheſies in all the Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the later times, chiefly <hi>the two Witneſſes;</hi> a matter at this time much ſpoken of, and about which godly men are diverſly minded.</p>
            <p>I am not willing to enter upon it now, but promiſe the <hi>Reader,</hi> he ſhall ſuddenly have it in an entyre Tract, for it lies ready by me for the Preſſe. From the <hi>Gentiles</hi> therefore, I come to the time of the end belonging to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> ſet down in <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.11, 12. <hi>And from the time that the daily ſacrifice ſhall be taken away, and the abhomination that maketh deſolate, ſet up, there ſhall be a thouſand two hundred and ninety dayes. Bleſſed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the thouſand three hundred and five and thirty dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt certain, that Jeſus Chriſt by his death, did put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all Jewiſh ſacrifices; he did (I ſay) <hi>Iure,</hi> and in right deſtroy them vertually by his owne ſacrifice, the fulneſſe and end of all their ſhadowes: Notwithſtanding <hi>facto,</hi> and actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his death many years, and by divers ſteps and degrees. For after the taking and ſacking of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by <hi>Titus,</hi> the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie not deſtroyed, the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſtill there inhabited, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued their vaine worſhip with more ignorant zeale then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>For 1. In the Reign of <hi>Adrian</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, who built and dedicated a Temple in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Jupiter Olympius,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118389:18"/>at which the <hi>Jewes</hi> being offended, rebelled and made head, and in the end were overcome and diſperſed, and the Citie named <hi>Aelia,</hi> and given into the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> whereas before untill that time, they had not ceaſed there, from ſacrifice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Being expelled the Citie, yet they continued their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions in the Countrey, and built an Altar under the Oak <hi>Mamre</hi> (where the Angels appeared to <hi>Abraham</hi>) and forced the Merchants which came to the Faires to ſacrifice thereon, otherwiſe they ſhould not traffique. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed the Altar, and built there a Church for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the dayes of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, and profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Chriſtians, in deſpight of the Chriſtian faith, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called the <hi>Jewes</hi> which were diſperſed to and fro, to return into their own land, gave them licenſe to build the Temple, and to re-eſtabliſh the Leviticall ſervice, and furniſhed them with work-men, money, materialls, and other neceſſaries out of the publique ſtock. The <hi>Jewes</hi> embracing ſo large a grant, attempted the building of the Temple, laid the foundation not wholly razed down before, wherein they were met by a ſpeciall hand of God: For a fearfull Earth-quake, with thunder, lightning, and fire-balls from Heaven, in one night deſtroyed all their worke and tools, and totally overthrew the foundation of the Temple: ſo that they were conſtrained to forbeare their work, and all further proceeding; and after that time the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ſacrifices did for ever ceaſe.</p>
            <p>It is alſo memorable, how <hi>Cyril</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> told the <hi>Jewes</hi> of this Propheſie; and ſeeing no admonition or perſwaſion would prevaile, he openly profeſſed, that now the time was come of which Chriſt ſpake unto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.2.</note> concerning the Temple, <hi>There ſhall not be left here one ſtone upon another, that ſhall not be thrown down.</hi> This total deſolation of the Temple, under the reign of <hi>Julian</hi> (in which the <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> ſacrifices were wholly taken away) fell out in the <hi>year</hi> 365. to which 1290. being added, doe make up 1655. The time deſigned for the riſing and beginning of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> after their long diſperſion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118389:18"/>
            <p> And here for the <hi>Readers</hi> better underſtanding, three things I ſhall propound to him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I do not underſtand (though many doe) any generall converſion of the <hi>Iewes</hi> at this time unto the faith, by the preaching of the Goſpell, but only ariſing amongſt them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a civill account, to recover their own Countrey.</p>
            <p>About this time (namely the <hi>yeare</hi> 1655.) if not before; my opinion is (and grounded I conceive on the holy word) that the Turk with great Forces will come into <hi>Italy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40.</note> 
               <hi>At the time of the end ſhall the King of the South puſh at him;</hi> that is, come out againſt the Pope, yet ſo, as he ſhall effect little or nothing, but ſuddenly depart: For <hi>tidings out of the Eaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 11.44.</note> 
               <hi>and out of the North ſhall trouble him;</hi> that is, news ſhall be brought unto him of an inſurrection of the <hi>Iewes</hi> through all parts of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, making head, forming themſelves into a Body, and entring into the land of <hi>Iudea. The firſt-ſhall ſay to Sion, behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.27.</note> 
               <hi>behold them, and I will give to Ieruſalem one that bringeth good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</hi> It ſeems to hold forth the Meſſengers of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which ſhall paſſe from place, to place with tidings of their deſigne, and to bring others in, for the ſooner and better effecting of it.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the <hi>Grand Signeor</hi> is ſaid <hi>to be troubled:</hi> and no marvail: For</p>
            <p n="1">1. He knows well, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> are a great people, and for wealth, and warlike abilities, able to cope with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Monarch in the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are domeſtick Enemies, beſetting him before and behind, eating out the bowels and revenues of his State.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their riſing is ſudden, from all parts of <hi>Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and their faction grows exceeding ſtrong before he hears of it: So that the ſuddenneſs of it did preſage ſome evil event; as is ever obſerved amongſt <hi>Politicians,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.2.6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He is the more <hi>troubled,</hi> as being with his Forces at ſuch a diſtance from them.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, who knows, but he ſhall be <hi>troubled</hi> now, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring an old tradition which the Turks have; that <hi>at laſt they ſhall be ſubdued and deſtroyed by the children of Iſaak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here by the way, take notice, that the <hi>Turk</hi> having brought
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118389:19"/>his Forces out of <hi>Aſia</hi> &amp; <hi>Affrica</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> againſt the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 15.12. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.10, 11.</note> or rather Antichriſtians: This I take to be <hi>the drying up of the river Eupbrates, &amp; the waters thereof, that the way of the Kings of the Eaſt might be prepared.</hi> The meaning ſeems to be thus; the power and ſtrength of the <hi>Turkes</hi> being in Chriſtendom, the <hi>Jewes</hi> (improving the advantage and opportunity of the time) wil riſe, and repair to their own land, and by a ſtrong hand re-enter and take the poſſeſſion of it. And this they ſhall do (as I ſaid before) only upon a
<note n="*" place="margin">Hence it is ſaid they ſhall take the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18. and after the Kingdom ſhall be given them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.44. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. <hi>Ezek</hi> 38.8, 9, 10, 11.</note> Civill account, taking example from other Nations, to ſhake off the yoke of Tyrants, and to be a free people.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Jewes</hi> being entred into their own Countrey: <hi>The Turke ſhall goe forth with great fury to deſtroy, and utterly to make away many. And here begins the time of trouble, ſuch as never was ſince there was a Nation, even to that ſame time.</hi> Moſt cruell and bloody warres between the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Turkes.</hi> This conflict ſhall be (for the moſt part) in <hi>Judea: And he ſhall plant the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of his Palace between the ſeas in the glorious holy mountain:</hi> that is, the borders, or continent betwixt <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and the <hi>Mediterranean.</hi> Of this warre, and place ſpeaketh <hi>Ezekiel. In the later dayes thou ſhalt come into the land that is brought backe from the ſword, and is gathered out of many people, againſt the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Iſrael, which have been alwayes waſt: But it is brought forth of the Nations, and they ſhall dwell ſafely all of them. Thou ſhalt aſcend, and come like a ſtorme, thou ſhalt be like a cloud to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>thou and all thy hands with thee,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Zechariah, I will gather all Nations againſt Jeruſalem, and the Citie ſhall be taken, and the houſes rifled, and the women raviſhed, and half of the Citie ſhall goe forth into captivity, and the reſidue of the people ſhall not be cut off from the Citie. Then ſhall the Lord goe forth and fight againſt thoſe Nations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreover as this War is expreſſed in holy Scripture, and the place, ſo the continuance of it, how long it ſhall be. <hi>Bleſſed is he that waiteth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>and cometh to the thouſand three hundred &amp; five and thirty dayes.</hi> This later number is more then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer by 45. <hi>years.</hi> And ſo long ſhall this war continue between the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Turks,</hi> namely from the year 1655. to 1700. Sometimes the one getting the better, ſometimes the other.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118389:19"/> 3. Theſe years being expired, about the year 1700.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael the great Prince will ſtand up for his people. Behold hee cometh with the clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him, &amp;c. This is the</hi> SET TIME <hi>in which the Lord will ariſe and have mercy upon Sion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.13.</note> 
               <hi>His feet ſhall ſtand in that day upon the Mount of Olives, which is before Jeruſalem on the Eaſt: and the Mount of Olives ſhall cleave in the midſt thereof toward the Eaſt, and toward the Weſt, and there ſhall be a very great valley, and halfe of the mountaine ſhall remove to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the North, and halfe of it toward the ſouth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>And he will plead with them there for his people, and for his heritage Iſrael.</hi> The Turk now totally and finally ſhall be deſtroyed. His army probably, beſide the Sea of <hi>Gennezaret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.11. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.8. <hi>Am.</hi> 9.14, 15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.21, 22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.31. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.19, 20. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.22.24. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.19, 20.</note> otherwiſe called the lake of <hi>Tiberias,</hi> and the Turk himſelfe at, or neer <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Upon this ſhall follow a ſpeedy and ſudden converſion of the <hi>Jewes: In one day, and at once,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, they ſhall dwell in their owne Land in ſafety, inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite all the parts of it as before; their Countrey ſhall be more fertile and populous then ever it was, a moſt flouriſhing State of Church and Common-wealth. There ſhall be, after this victory once obtained, no ſeparation any more of the <hi>tenne Tribes</hi> from the other two, but both ſhall make one entire Kingdom. All Nations ſhall come in to them, and honour them, and willingly, or perforce ſubmit unto the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But to return to the year 1655. It is the opinion of many, (and I am of the ſame mind) that ſixe thouſand yeares from the Creation, doe meet with the ending of this year 1655. which is neer at hand, and great Revolutions are look't for at that time: For the particulars I find them not expreſt, but to me, theſe fearefull and terrible changes ſeeme to be theſe five.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Turke,</hi> his coming againſt <hi>Italy</hi> with ſuch multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, will fill all <hi>Europe</hi> with terrour, and amazement; and howſoever his ſtay here ſhall be ſhort (as was ſaid before) yet it will be the occaſion, and riſe of marvellous changes to follow afterwards.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In this year will the Lord moſt eminently appear, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Earth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag</hi> 2.22.</note> and <hi>overthrowing the Thrones of Kingdomes</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118389:20"/>where in <hi>Europe:</hi> By this time (I verily think) <hi>the Thrones will be ſet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.11.</note> 
               <hi>and the Ancient of dayes ſitting thereon.</hi> The Prophet ſaith, <hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee, but they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed.</hi> Hitherto what God hath done in <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, overturning, overturning</hi> (the Biſhops firſt, the King next, the Parliament laſt) it is not obſerved, as the righteous hand of God.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>All things continue</hi> (ſaith the Scoffer) <hi>as they were from the beginning of the Creation.</hi> But know this, in the year 1655. the Viall ſhall be ſo full, poured out ſo faſt, and lye ſo cloſe &amp; hot upon the perſecuting powers of the world, as they ſhall then ſee, and be aſhamed, begin to take notice that it is the wrath of the Lamb which followes after them. It is reported of <hi>Moles,</hi> that a ſhort time before they die, they ſee a little, but never before. So the blind Pope, and his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and the Kings of the earth, as blind as he, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the finall extirpation of their State, ſomething they will ſee, as of God fighting from Heaven againſt them, though they <hi>repent not to give him glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. At this time, great changes and revolutions will be, in reſpect both of perſons and things: For howſoeve I am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that every change amongſt us ſhall be for good unto the Nation, as this preſent Government, and what followes, a great deale better then the former; yet I queſtion, whether the Lord <hi>will throughly purge his floore,</hi> in ſweeping out all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and ſelfiſh men, untill that time: But ſome wil ſtil creep in unawares, not ſerving the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellie. Nevertheleſſe this I would have the <hi>Reader</hi> obſerve, that about the yeare 1655.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.8.7.</note> the righteous alone ſhall flouriſh, and be exalted. <hi>A two-edged ſword is in their hand, to execute vengeance upon the Heathen, and puniſhment upon the people: to bind their Kings with chaines, and their Nobles with fetters of iron. To execute upon them the judgement written.</hi> And this Supream Power ſhall abide with them four or five yeares without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption, untill they have broken in pieces the <hi>fourth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Another terrible and fearfull change, in likelihood will fall out in the year 1655. or the year after, that is the
<note n="*" place="margin">There are ſome <hi>Propheſies</hi> which mention the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Rome</hi> in the yeare 6000. from the Creation.</note> ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and burning of the Citie of <hi>Rome.</hi> After which <hi>it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118389:20"/>be inhabited, neither ſhall it be dwelt in from generation to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; but wilde Beaſts of the Deſart ſhall lie there, and their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall be full of dolefull Creatures. And Owles ſhall dwell there, and Satyrs ſhall dance there.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.2.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>And the wild beaſts of the Iſlands ſhall cry in their deſolate houſes, and Dragons in their pleaſant palaces, and her time is neer come, and her dayes ſhall not be prolonged.</hi> And this inſtrumentally ſhall be done by the Saints of the moſt high, whoſe hearts and hands the Lord will raiſe up for that work. It is poſſible that the Pope, Cardinals, Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. may eſcape, as being reſerved to periſh after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with the worſhippers of the Beaſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 31.8.</note> as <hi>Balaam</hi> periſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Midianites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The laſt is the riſing of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> of which I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and ſhall make no repetition.</p>
            <p>Having opened ſome <hi>Propheſies,</hi> and applyed them, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the grace received, I come now to the other particular, which is to ſhew the time in which wee are, and our preſent work: And this is a ſpecial <hi>Voyce from the Temple unto the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the generall I have expreſſed my opinion already: Chriſt <hi>hath his right foot on the Sea, and his left foot on the Earth.</hi> So then <hi>to follow the Lamb,</hi> it is to break in pieces thoſe two Powers, <hi>Kingly,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian. Who is on my ſide</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Who? Throw her downe. Come againſt her from the utmoſt border,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.26.</note> 
               <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen her ſtore-houſes, caſt her up as heapes, and deſtroy her utterly, let nothing of her be left.</hi> There is now a price put into your hands, a faire opportunity, and a door opened before you. <hi>He that letted is taken out of the way.</hi> If a Marriner ſhould be asked in winter why he is at home, and not at Sea; to ſpeake of the unſeaſonableneſſe of the time, might be a reaſon ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: but if the Winter be paſt, and the ſeaſon good, here he hath not the like excuſe to make for himſelfe. When Kingly power ſtood, and the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, which was worſe, and the laſt <hi>Parliament</hi> little better; that ſome in Authority did little good, much might be ſaid for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe: But now ſeeing all theſe things are removed, what will our next Governours have to ſay for themſelves, if they doe not appear and act earneſtly for juſt and righteous things. If
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118389:21"/>a man did certainly know the day of his death: what appetite or deſire could he have to meat, an hour before he was to dye? It may be thoſe things which I here write, ſome will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: but howſoever I ſhall diſcharge mine owne conſcience: and therefore this I do declare with confidence to the world, that corrupt men, and ſelfe-ſeekers, their trade is coming down, and two years ſhall not be expired (mark it) but they ſhall vomit up what they have gotten by injuſtice, falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, bribery, &amp;c. and God ſhall caſt it out of their bellie.</p>
            <p>But more particularly to the <hi>preſent worke:</hi> Such as will act well hereafter, and <hi>ſerve their generation,</hi> they muſt in moſt things do otherwiſe, and contrary to what others have done before them. I ſhall only inſtance ſome particulars briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They muſt be active, and quickly diſpatch the buſineſs which they take in hand; and not to tell people as others u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually did, <hi>of the Thankes of the Houſe, and that it was under Debate, referred to a Committee, &amp;c.</hi> and here was all. But let Petitioners be ſpeedily relieved in their juſt applications. I have ſeen at the foot of great houſes, Images ſet out in ſuch a poſture, as if the building lay on their backs: Such pictures we had, as made ſhew to have the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth on their ſhoulders, whereas in truth (for moſt of them) neither the one, nor the other had any reall help or ſupportance from them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They muſt not ſeek nor deſire to grow rich and great in the world, by being in Authority, but advance the Publique Intereſt, and not their owne. A thing formerly not practiſed by many, but left the care of publick concernment to enrich themſelves.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that many of them, who before the <hi>Parliament</hi> began, were not worth two or three hundred pounds a year, have now made it up, ſome to a thouſand, ſome to fifteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, ſome to two thouſand pounds a year, and more. Theſe muſt be ſerved, as <hi>Eſop</hi> did his fellow-ſervant, he gave him warm water to drink, by which means he vomited up the <hi>ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len figges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a work now proper to <hi>the higher Powers,</hi> to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full what men they appoint, as Juſtices and Magiſtrates in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118389:21"/>Common-wealth; hitherto in Towne and Countrey ſuch have been in many places, as have moſt groſly abuſed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, exerciſed even an arbritary power where they liv'd, and done what they liſt; as knowing if their inſolencies and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitances ſhould be complained of, they had a
<note n="*" place="margin">Of this thing, wee had a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable example in <hi>Hull,</hi> where one Maſter <hi>Shaw,</hi> a notable <hi>Turn-coate,</hi> and <hi>Time-ſerver</hi> as lives, hath committed ſuch ſcandalous actions as ſeldome are heard of, yet no Juſtice could paſſe againſt him, by reaſon of the corrupt Mayor. The things are ſo foule againſt them both, as honeſt men wonder they ſhould be ſuffered: But ſo long as the laſt Parliament ſtood, Mr. <hi>Shaw</hi> was ſupported in all the miſchiefe he plotted, either againſt the Towne, or honeſt men. The laſt Speaker, Baron <hi>Thorp,</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> know who I meane, and who did helpe <hi>Shaw,</hi> to make three or foure unworthy Aldermen at a clap, all Brothers, and to have what Mayor and Sheriffs, <hi>Shaw</hi> would, to carry on his Deſigne, which was to diſquiet the peace of the place, and affront the honeſt party. I heare hee ſtudieth to get favour amongſt thoſe who are now in place: But that no honeſt man may be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him, this I teſtifie publiquely, and of knowledge, he is a moſt corrupt man, and hitherto countenanced by men, as corrupt and rotten as himſelfe.</note> friend in the Houſe, would bear them out in ſpight of all accuſers.</p>
            <p>Hence a man every where, might have ſeen that in <hi>Solomon</hi> fulfilled: <hi>When the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. How many years hath it been under <hi>Debate in the Houſe concerning the propagation of the Goſpell.</hi> Now I deſire every one that fears God, to obſerve, what progreſſe they have made herein. This I affirme to be true, they have left ſtanding in the Nation, a <hi>Clergy,</hi> or <hi>generation of Prieſts,</hi> more ſcandalous, prophane, wicked, inſufficient, &amp;c. then was in the Biſhops time, and before they began to ſit: Notwithſtanding they would ſend their Acts, to theſe wretches, that they ſhould pray and give Thanks for them. Whereas <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſent to <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>to lift vp his prayer for the remnant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe unworthy men, are to be removed from their unſanctified places and ſtanding, the word of God is clear for it; but whether he will ſo far honour our next Governours, in putting them upon ſo glorious a worke, a little time will ſhew.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Be ſure that ye be real, and faithfull to ſuch men, whom you know, to be reall and faithful to that Cauſe, and Worke you are upon. Of late, <hi>Turn coats, Time-ſervers, Apoſtates,</hi> and ſuch like, have been moſt favoured, ſooneſt heard, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118389:22"/>The which was one ſpeciall cauſe of their ruine, and will deſtroy others if they do the like. As fire taken off from the hearth, and put to the Thatch, will burn down the houſe; Even ſo, if men in place, with-draw their affection from honeſt and good men, to act for unworthy ones, they cannot ſtand. <hi>Let them aſſociate themſelves, and they ſhall be broken, take counſell together, and it ſhall come to nought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 101.6.</note> As <hi>the Lord will ſet apart him that is godly:</hi> And <hi>David</hi> ſaith <hi>mine eyes ſhall be upon the faithfull of the land:</hi> So in chooſing men to publique employment, carnall relations muſt be laid aſide, and men fearing God pitch't upon. It would be worth the while to conſider, how many are in place, who hate to be reform'd, count it their grace that they are graceleſſe: yea, deſpight the ſpirit of grace in Saints. If a man ſhould ſow Tares in his Field, or plant thornes and thiſtles in his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, would it be a wonder afterward, to ſee fruit according to the kind he hath ſown and planted? Thoſe that do ſet and plant in the Common-wealth, crafty men, covetous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull fellows, I meane as to have places of great truſt, and concernment, if they deceive the State; no marvail, <hi>Who will expect grapes of thornes, or figs of thiſtles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. There is another abuſe which honeſt men deſire ſpeedily to have reform'd, namely a multitude of unneceſſary and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Officers, publiquely employed in civill affairs, whereby the Revenues of the Common-wealth are extreamly waſted: which men, if removed, not onely many thouſand pounds a year would be ſaved, but the worke ſpeedier, and much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter done. Beſides, it is well known, that ſome of the late Parliament, have deviſed new Offices where there was none before,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> and whereof there is no uſe in the world, purpoſely to ſet in ſome of their own kindred for ſallarie.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whereas many have gotten great eſtates, by falſhood, deceit, unfaithfulneſſe, done many unjuſt actions, and doe fraudulently detain much of the publique treaſure in their hands, and ſome are ready to manifeſt and prove ſo much. It is deſired, not only that ſome men may be appointed, to heare and receive the Informations, and Charges, which ſhall be brought forth againſt ſuch Delinquents: but ſpeciall care
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118389:22"/>be taken about the choiſe of them, as that they be <hi>able men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch as feare God, men of truth, hating covetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As thoſe laſt men in power were for the moſt part men moſt corrupt, ſo ordinarily they ſet none in places under them, but men corrupt and rotten as themſelves: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no marvail though ſome much deſired to have their <hi>olde Maſters</hi> in again, for they knew, they were NONE SUCH to ſerve their turne. The glaſſe-window lets in light, but keeps out winde and raine: I hope to ſee ſuch in place, as will heare and receive the truth, the whole truth, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the truth, and keep back partiality, reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, relations, private Intereſts.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For the <hi>Regulating of the Laws,</hi> and other corruptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, here it is expected, that things be now done ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and effectually. <hi>The turning of the Law into Engliſh,</hi> no way eaſed or leſſened the grievances of the people: <hi>Curſed is he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently.</hi> Remember the TWO PLAGUES of this Nation, PRIESTS and LAWYERS. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt let goe out of thy hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 20.42.</note> 
               <hi>a man whom I appointed to utter deſtruction, therefore thy life ſhall go for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Take heed of making Parties, and running into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as the former ever did, to carry on, particular and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate deſignes.</p>
            <p>The worke before you is publique, and generall, and therefore be not divided in Schiſmes and Factions, but unanimouſly accord together in the preſent worke of the Lord. In rayſing up a materiall houſe, when the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſweetly agree together, the building goes forward apace: ſo here. How farre the Lord will carry on his work inſtrumentally by ſuch as ſhall be next in power, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of theſe, and other things I know not, neither what the Lord intends to doe by them, concerning <hi>the breaking in pieces the fourth Monarch, and Antichriſtian Kingdome:</hi> But this I know, if theſe come not up to the work, others ſhortly will: For it ſhall not be left undone beyond the yeare 1655. A people
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118389:23"/>then ſhall be created, to fulfill the will of God (and he will put it into their hearts) in order to the Propheſies of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>For the viſion is yet for an appointed time: but in the end it ſhall ſpeake, and not lie.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have conſidered that there are two things, wherein thou maiſt be much unſatisfied concerning this ſubject.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How to deſtroy the <hi>little horne,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> can ſtand with <hi>Tolleration of Religion,</hi> and <hi>liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> allowed by the preſent Government, and upon juſt and good grounds.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To break the <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> tends not to make this Common-wealth happy and flouriſhing, which <hi>the higher Powers</hi> are to ſeek after: but to preſerve Peace, and ſo Trade with other Nations, is much better for our proſperity, wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and happineſſe. I ſhall anſwer both.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdom,</hi> is a <hi>State</hi> guilty of blood, and accordingly to be arreigned and executed. In <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. after <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſaid to be deſtroyed, the reaſon of it is ſhewed in the laſt verſe. <hi>In her was found the blood of the Prophets, and of Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the earth:</hi> So that hence it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that no wilfull murtherer, more juſtly can be put to death, then the power of the Beaſt deſtroyed, for ſhedding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the times may be, ſome acts of Juſtice may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, which afterward ought, and muſt be done. <hi>David</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.29.</note> that <hi>the ſonnes of Zerviah were too hard for him:</hi> yet <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> following (being in a better capacity) put one of them to death, and juſtly too. For a more cleare illuſtration: Though murther be diſcovered, and the perſon known, yet no execution can be done upon him, till he fall into the hands
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118389:23"/>of Juſtice. Indeed then, if the Magiſtrate neglect his duty, and ſuffer him to eſcape, he wraps himſelf in the blood and guilt of the Malefactor. That <hi>blood-guiltineſſe,</hi> lies on the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kingdome, this hath been known to Saints in former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but <hi>the ſonnes of Zerviah</hi> were alwayes too hard for them: but now, when the power ſhall be in their hands, not to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute judgment upon the murtherer, is (as I conceive) to be no otherwiſe then acceſſary to the blood of the Prophets, and of the Saints, <hi>in the great City Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To give liberty &amp; tolleration I am clearly for; yet ſo, as the known will of God be fulfilled concerning the work of this preſent time: And therefore we muſt diſtinguſh between perſons and things. Perſons are to be tollerated, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly minded in point of Religion; but where the vengeance of the Lord, and the vengeance of his Temple,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.</note> is expreſly cal'd for, and to be executed thus, and thus: What tolleration is to be granted here in ſuch a caſe, I deſire thoſe to conſider of, who are <hi>ſpecially concerned</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſeeing I have mentioned ſo often the <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdom,</hi> to be deſtroyed by the <hi>Ancient of dayes, ſitting upon his Throne, &amp;c.</hi> It will not be amiſſe, that I give the <hi>Reader</hi> my meaning more fully.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdom,</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> was firſt erected againſt Jeſus Chriſt, that is, to corrupt his word, and worſhip, and to deſtroy his people, under a pretence of blaſphemy, hereſie, ſchiſme, &amp;c. The which in Popery, Prelacy, and Presbytery, hath been both profeſt and proſecuted; whereby much inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood hath been ſhed, and would be ſtill, if the Magiſtrate would give his power to them. Beſides, by this <hi>Antichriſtian State,</hi> againſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, a Church, Miniſtery, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, &amp; Government hath been deviſed, and ſet up: All which the Saints neer the end, will call to an account; and finding the ſame to be guilty of innocent blood, and a main let to the preſent exaltation of Chriſts Kingdome, will judicially give ſentence, <hi>that it be thrown downe, and be no more at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reward her, even as ſhe hath rewarded you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>and double unto her double according to her works: In the cup which ſhe hath filled, fill her double.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay; whereas this <hi>bloody Kingdome,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118389:24"/>moſt falſly judged you in the Saints which were before, to be <hi>Hereticks, Blaſphemers, Schiſmaticks,</hi> and perſecuted you by impriſonment, baniſhment, confiſcation of goods, yea death it ſelf: And would not ſuffer you to walk in the faith and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Goſpel, <hi>Reward her, even as ſhe rewarded you;</hi> that is, as God hath put the power of Nations into your hand, and the <hi>day and judgement of Babylon</hi> being now come. Whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Lord carries you forth, execute the vengeance of the Lord, and of his temple upon the <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdome.</hi> Here ſtill I ſpeak of things, and not of perſons.</p>
            <p>To the other Objection I anſwer thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The glory of God in fulfilling his word, is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd before all outward proſperity. A Heathen could ſay, <hi>Let Juſtice be done, and the world periſh:</hi> Shall Saints then, hold back their hands, from executing the righteous Judgments of the Lord, only through a baſe fear of worldly inconveniences.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.30.</note> 
               <hi>There is no wiſdome, nor underſtanding, nor counſell againſt the Lord.</hi> If he be breaking now (as certainly he is) the <hi>fourth Monarch,</hi> we and they may take counſel together, but it ſhall come to nought. What man, ſeeing his neighbours houſe on fire, would willingly ſet his own by it, for ſo they would both burn and fall together. The Lords fire is already kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Thrones and Kingdomes: And therefore the further off we keep, from aſſociating our ſelves with them, from coming near them in Leagues and Covenants, the more likely it is, that our Common-wealth wil be happy, and flouriſh.</p>
            <p>But 3. I would not have the people of this Nation to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, that theſe <hi>Changings</hi> and <hi>Turnings</hi> in the world, are in order to their better trading; God intends it otherwiſe: It's for trading indeed, but for his owne: To breake the Kings, Merchants, and great men of the Earth, that the Kingdomes of this world may be his, and his Chriſts. Worldly men have had their time for Trade, and they have had a long time of it. The Lord now is putting an end to that, and ſetting up a better.</p>
            <p>I write this for my Countrey-mens ſake, to let them know, howſoever I hope, Thoſe which ſhall be next in place, will doe juſt and good things, take off what burthens they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118389:24"/>can, and make the Nation as happy and proſperous as they are able: Yet I have no hope, that the Times will be any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for civill Trade, but more troubleſome, and warrs daily increaſe: And therefore they ſhould now begin to look up to God, and after his work, and the <hi>Great Trade</hi> which he is carrying on: and with-draw their minds from this <hi>old world,</hi> which is periſhing, and going out, and prepare for <hi>the world to come whereof we ſpeake,</hi> wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.</note> and which will be much better for them, if they be of that number, who <hi>looke for the bleſſed hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>and the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Concluſion, there is one word more from <hi>the Temple to the higher Powers,</hi> and ſo I have done. And it concerns a main thing, in order to our late great victory at Sea, which the Lord gave us over the <hi>Dutch.</hi> It was ſome trouble unto many, when they heard that the <hi>Holland Merchant Ships</hi> were returned ſafely home, and not met with by our Fleet: It is true, the Lord could have given them into our hands, but he would not. And why not the one, as well as the other? The reaſon is (as the Lord hath put it ſtrongly on my heart to have it known) In this he tels us, what our proper worke is, namely not to look after Merchants, as to grow great and rich by the wealth of other Nations, but to break their power &amp; ſtrength in pieces. The Lord gave their men of Warr into our hands, not their Merchant Ships. Speaking here I ſay, as it were from heaven, that it is not prizes, or the Enemies goods, our hearts or hands ſhould deſirouſly be upon: But to deſtroy <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſtain the glory of Kings and Kingdoms, and lay low the high and great mountains of the earth.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. 22.10.</bibl> 
               <hi>Seale not the ſayings of the Propheſie of this Book, for the time is at hand.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſ. 14.9.</bibl> 
               <hi>Who is wiſe, and he ſhall underſtand theſe things? prudent, and hee ſhall know them? For the wayes of the Lord are right, and the juſt ſhall walke in them; but the tranſgreſſors ſhall fall therein.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
